<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE documentation SYSTEM 'jmax.dtd'>
<documentation title="Installation">
<!-- $Id: install.xml,v 1.2 2006-03-15 04:44:50 matju Exp $ -->
<!--
        GridFlow Installation
        Copyright (c) 2001,2002,2003,2004,2005 by Mathieu Bouchard
-->
<section name="Hardware and Software you Probably Need">
<p>Required Computer/Processor (one of...):<list>
	<li>PC : AMD K6/K7/K8 or Intel P2/P3/P4 (absolute minimum is 386)</li>
	<li>Macintosh : G3/G4/G5</li>
	<li>Corel NetWinder : StrongARM V4L</li>
	<li>HP iPaq : some processor that works like the NetWinder</li>
	<li>could work on SiliconGraphics and SPARCstation with a little nurture.</li>
</list></p>
<p>Required OS (one of...):<list>
	<li>Linux (most any variant) (recommended)</li>
	<li>MacOS 10.2 or later (experimental)</li>
	<li>Windows with MinGW (very experimental)</li>
</list></p>
<p>Required Software:<list>
	<li>Ruby 1.6.6 or more recent (1.8.0 recommended) (make sure you have the *.so and *.h files)
	(on MacOS you may have to remove or hide the existing one and install a more complete package)</li>
</list></p>
<p>Dataflow Software :<list>
	<li>PureData 0.36 or later (recommended)</li>
</list></p>
<p>Multimedia Components (optional):<list>
	<li>libSDL (Simple Directmedia Layer)</li>
	<li>libjpeg</li>
	<li>libpng</li>
	<li>libmpeg3 (.mpg reader, HeroineWarrior's)</li>
	<li>libquicktime (.mov reader/writer, Burkhard Plaum's or HeroineWarrior's) </li>
	<li>libmpeg (.mpg reader, Greg Ward's, old)</li>
	<li>Apple QuickTime (.mov reader/writer)</li>
	<li>Ascii Art Library (aalib)</li>
	<li>PCI video digitizer card  (and Video4linux 1 driver)</li>
	<li>USB camera (and Video4linux 1 driver)</li>
</list></p>
<p>Developer Tools (roll-your-own):<list>
	<li>GNU C++ Compiler (gcc/g++) version 3.x or maybe 2.95</li>
	<li>GNU Make (gmake)</li>
	<li>CVS (for upgrading/collaboration)</li>
	<li>Ruby library "xmlparser" (optional, for editing documentation)</li>
	<li>Developer Tools CD dec 2002 (if MacOS 10.2)</li>
	<li>XCODE (if MacOS 10.3)</li>
	<li>FINK (if MacOS 10)</li>
</list></p>
<p>NOTE: Apparently GCC 2.x has problems dealing with *.a components; if that
affects you, use *.so files instead.</p>
</section>

<section name="Downloading from CVS">
<p>The CVS has the absolute latest version of GridFlow, but it's not guaranteed to be working, whereas
the actual releases are more tested.</p>
<p>However you may have various reasons to use the CVS edition, so here's how:</p>
<p>Make sure you have the <k>cvs</k> program installed.</p>
<p><k>mkdir -p ~/src/gridflow</k> (make a directory; it could be called otherwise if you like)</p>
<p><k>cd ~/src/gridflow</k> (go in that directory)</p>
<p><k>cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.gridflow.ca:/home/cvs/gridflow login</k> (the password is blank)</p>
<p><k>cvs -d :pserver:anonymous@cvs.gridflow.ca:/home/cvs/gridflow checkout .</k> (download the first time)</p>
<p>And the subsequent times, you only do this:</p>
<p><k>cd ~/src/gridflow</k></p>
<p><k>cvs update -dP</k></p>
</section>

<section name="Installation instructions (incl. compilation)">
<list>
<li>Install Ruby. Make sure it contains <k>ruby.h</k> and <k>intern.h</k> and related files. It's also
recommended to have <k>libruby.so</k>. Those extra files may be in a package called <k>ruby-dev</k>
if you are using RPM or DEB/FINK. If you are building Ruby yourself, it's better to configure ruby with
<k>--enable-shared</k>. If you install into a system directory, you may have to run <k>ldconfig</k>
after installing Ruby.</li>

<li>Download GridFlow from the website and uncompress it, or get it from the CVS server.</li>

<li>Run <k>./configure</k> from the <k>gridflow</k> directory. Make sure it detects all the components
you want to use with GridFlow. In MacOS you would normally use FINK to install:
	<k>libjpeg libjpeg-shlibs libpng-shlibs libpng3 libpng3-shlibs libmpeg libmpeg-shlibs</k>
</li>

<li>Note: you may have to set <k>CPLUS_INCLUDE_PATH</k> to indicate where to find *.h files, and you
may have to set both <k>LIBRARY_PATH</k> and <k>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</k> to indicate where to find
*.so  or *.aor *.dylib or *.bundle or *.dll or *.lib files.</li>

<li>Note: you can do <k>./configure --help</k> to get a list of supported
options. You can use them to ignore the presence of troublesome libraries
and select debugging level. With <k>--use-compiler</k> you should use a version of <k>g++</k>, not
directly a version of <k>gcc</k>, else you get <k>undefined symbol</k> problems. Some versions of gcc/g++
are troublesome.</li>

<li>Run <k>make</k> to produce the executables <k>gridflow.so</k> and <k>gridflow.pd_linux</k> or similar</li>
<li>Run <k>make install</k> to copy those executables and related files to their final locations.</li>
<li>Run <k>make test</k> just to verify that GridFlow isn't working too bad.</li>
<li>With a text editor, create <k>~/.gridflow_startup</k> and write something like
<k>GridFlow.data_path &lt;&lt; "/home/myself/gridflow/images"</k> to tell GridFlow where to find the
images used in the examples. You may add more lines like that one if you have folders containing images
or movies you want to use with GridFlow.</li>
<li>Loading GridFlow:<list>
	<li>PureData : With a text editor, modify or create <k>~/.pdrc</k> and write <k>-lib gridflow</k>. </li>
	<li>ImpureData : In the ".pdrc editor", add <k>gridflow</k> to the list of libraries.</li>
	<li>plain Ruby : the command <k>require "gridflow"</k> will load gridflow.so.</li>
</list>
Note that on MacOS the dot-files are invisible in the Finder but you do
<k>cd ~/Desktop; ln -s ../.pdrc "PureData Configuration"</k> to make an alias on the Desktop.
Note also that on Windows the dot-files are even more trouble.</li>
</list>
</section>

<section name="Other Tips">
<list>

<li>you just did a CVS update and now the program does not compile, or
crashes, or changes didn't go through. 
	<list>
	<li>Did you forget the "make install" step?</li>
	<li>If a new directory is created, you need to do <k>cvs update -d</k>.
	  Many people just add that option to their configuration of the CVS software.</li>
	<li>When some kinds of changes have happened, you may have to rerun the <k>configure</k>
	program before redoing <k>make</k>. If you had previously reconfigured with specific options,
	don't forget to use them again in this case.</li>
	<li>Maybe matju forgot to upload part of an important change. Tell him.</li>
	</list></li>


<li>PureData Crashing:
	<list>
	<li>you can start the debugger like <k>gdb `which pd` core.24255</k> where the latter part
	is the name of a RAM dump file. You can enable those dumps using the shell command
	<k>ulimit -c unlimited</k>. To avoid dumping, you can also start Pd from within the debugger
	using <k>gdb `which pd`</k> then <k>run</k> then cause the crash.</li>
	<li>In GDB, after a crash, you can use the <k>where</k> to find out what Pd was doing at the moment
	of the crash. If instead Pd is frozen, you can force it to crash using Ctrl+C in the terminal.
	</li>
	<li>To quit GDB use the <k>quit</k> command. (really.)</li>
</list></li>
</list>
</section>
</documentation>
